בוקר טוב. Boker tov. All right. So we pick up on דף
צדי. Daf Tzadi. We're in the פרק perek of האישה רבה, Ha'isha
Raba, which is one of the more challenging פרקים perakim in יבמות.
Yevamot. Challenging in a couple of ways. Both because the logic
of the first משנה mishna is very hard to understand why this
woman has all these negative consequences against her and why it's worse
when she operates ברשות birshut than שלא ברשות. shelo birshut. It's challenging
because just the issues are, you know, the סוגיות sugyot are denser
and more complicated.
And and it's and also because it introduces an idea of a
stuff, which is a סוגיא sugya we're in the middle of, is
the rabbis' ability to make some like radical innovations in terms of
יש כח לחכמים לעקור דבר מן התורה, yesh koach l'chachamim l'aker davar
min hatorah, there's the whole fact to believe an עד אחד ed
echad and so on. It also tends to be because there are
some of these really dense סוגיות sugyot and also some ש"ס Shas
סוגיות, sugyot, a פרק perek of יבמות Yevamot that is most learned
or I don't know most but certainly one of the פרקים perakim
of all the מסכת masechet that is particularly learned in the ישיבות.
yeshivot. So the issue that we are in the middle of is
understanding first of all this very complicated, like I said, not complicated,
well anyway, contradictory, logically challenging law in the משנה mishna which I
want to say a word about which is so the משנה mishna
states, thank you, I got two more; it's a two coffee day.
So there's the—what?
No, it's a combination. So the הלכה halacha in the משנה mishna
is that a woman goes ahead and gets a report that her
husband is dead, doesn't say one witness or two witnesses, and she
marries ברשות בית דין, birshut beit din, you know, with the allowance
of בית דין, beit din, and then her husband turns up alive
and it turns up and she basically has to get divorced from
both husbands and if there's a child it's ממזר mamzer from either
husband and she loses all of her rights etc. all these negative
consequences. However if she goes ahead and marries שלא ברשות בית דין,
shelo birshut beit din, she goes back to her first husband and
doesn't have any of these negative consequences. So this is of course
like boggles the mind; you know A: why the negative consequences in
the first place? and B: why is it worse when it's ברשות
birshut than when it's שלא ברשות? shelo birshut? So the very first
line of the גמרא, gemara, I don't know if you recognize this,
I'm going to, you know, said with the סתם stam voice of
the גמרא—it gemara was not a specific אמורא—said amora it chose to
interpret the word that when it's ברשות בית דין birshut beit din
means there was only one witness. And when it was שלא ברשות
בית דין, shelo birshut beit din, which has the non-negative consequences, which
at first שלא ברשות shelo birshut sounds like it's worse—she's operating unilaterally—it
said no that meant there were two witnesses and you didn't need
a special היתר. heter. So basically explained that the reason that there
weren't negative consequences in the end was really the end was better;
there was two witnesses. And the reason that you have the negative
consequences in the beginning was because—well why? Meaning okay, we get that
it's worse that there was only one witness but still why? I
mean if בית דין beit din gave her permission, why all the
negative consequences? And the גמרא gemara is then again the סתם stam
voice of the גמרא gemara introduces the idea because the only way
we can allow her to remarry on the force of one witness
is because
we assume that she's going to be דייקא ומינסבא, dayka u-mintsva, investigate
first before getting married and because we can really rely on because
that's a very sort
of radical thing to do to allow her to marry on one
witness, we have to back it up with the assumption that she's
aware of all of these terrible consequences and nevertheless she's looked into
it and has made certain. And that sort of allows it better
to be a basis for allowing her to remarry because, you know,
because if she's choosing to marry even knowing these consequences would await
her on the testimony of one witness we could assume that she's
investigated it well. So the גמרא gemara sort of frames it that
we needed to give her all these negative consequences in order to
find a mechanism somehow to legitimate why she can remarry on the
basis of עד אחד. ed echad. That's the way the גמרא gemara
explains it. Of course it's still very strange; this poor woman, what
is she to do? And maybe she doesn't have the ability to
investigate; she supposed to hire private investigators? What's she supposed to do?
It also assumes that she's aware of the negative consequences. Some אחרונים
acharonim say so then we should be obligated to tell her, hey
lady, before you remarry be aware that there's going to be all
these negative consequences. The גמרא gemara never indicates that we tell her.
It's very difficult to understand.
Yeah, she's in בבל Bavel and her husband made—exactly, exactly, exactly.
So it's very hard to understand. So I first wanted to share
with you what I thought was a sort of brilliant explanation that
Shamma Friedman offers, the תלמוד Talmud scholar, you know,
from Bar-Ilan
University sort of introducing the whole a whole way of learning גמרא—I
gemara mean he didn't create it obviously, but sort of is trying
to propagate a more sort of academic way of learning גמרא, gemara,
actually coming trying to come out with even his own ש"ס Shas
although that's very slow going yet, if anybody wants
to
get— Anyway,
so but still he doesn't have too many PhDs turned out apparently
because he's still got a long way to go. Anyway, his approach
is if you strip away the סתם Stam of the גמרא, Gemara,
which is you know the general way the academics do it, which
is you know let's try to see sort of what the approach
was before the סתם Stam of the גמרא, Gemara, there's no hint
to this idea of this radical re-reading of the משנה. Mishnah. The
reading of the משנה Mishnah that שברשות she'birshut means one witness and
שלא ברשות she'lo birshut means two witnesses. There's no hint that that's
the case in any of the statements of the אמוראים. Amoraim. And
that we should interpret the משנה כפשוטה Mishnah k'pshutah and שברשות, she'birshut,
in both cases let's say means one witness or I don't know,
maybe they both mean two, but that's not the difference. And it
means in one case you went ahead, and some there was some
evidence, you didn't bother to bring it to a בית דין Beis
Din to get a פסק, psak, you just operated on her own,
and that's שלא ברשות, she'lo birshut, it doesn't matter one or two,
you didn't go to the בית דין, Beis Din, that's שלא ברשות.
she'lo birshut. And ברשות birshut is she brought the evidence to the
בית דין Beis Din and the בית דין Beis Din ruled, but
it's not a difference of one or two. So again the question
is why the much more severe consequence when she operates through בית
דין Beis Din and why all this negative consequence anyway? So he
said this is not a קנס. knas. The פשט pshat of the
משנה Mishnah is not that it's a קנס knas and that it's
a punishment. The פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah is is that
when it's done ברשות בית דין, birshut Beis Din, what that does
is that recognizes officially recognizes the second marriage. And since it officially
recognizes the second marriage, and that's part of the חידוש chiddush of
חכמים Chachamim that on the basis of עד אחד ed echad and
on the basis of what normally would not be sufficient evidence they
could say we're going to allow you to remarry, and if we're
going to allow you to remarry, we're going to recognize that this
second marriage is binding even though normally we would not have had
sufficient evidence to do so. Our חידוש, chiddush, what we're doing משום
עגונה אקילו בה רבנן mishum agunah akilu bah rabanan to acknowledge to
give to recognize the testimony of one witness is we're going to
validate that and validate this second marriage. So now they validated the
second marriage and her husband shows up. So you know what her
הלכה halacha status is right now? Not that like רש״י Rashi says
based on the סתם Stam of the גמרא, Gemara, well she's now
committed adultery. No, no, no. She didn't commit adultery, she did it
based on בית דין. Beis Din. Her halachic status right now is
that she's married to two husbands. בית דין Beis Din recognized the
second marriage and they recognized and the first one... right,
no, the first one was a normal marriage. So she's so she's
now married to two husbands. So if she's married now to two
husbands, you understand why she needs a גט get from both husbands,
right? Because she's married to two husbands. The גמרא Gemara asks why
does she need a גט get from this? He goes you need
a גט get from this and you need a גט get from
this because she's now recognized as married to two husbands. Why are
these all these negative consequences? All these negative consequences because it's a
natural sort of not a punishment but it's a natural consequence of
the fact that I mean we've never had this animal before in
הלכה halacha of a woman married to two husbands. But now if
you're married to one husband and at the same time you're married
to another, then you lose all of your rights from either husband
because you don't have rights from this husband if you're married to
another and you don't have rights from that because you're married to
another. So you're like losing all of your כתובה kesubah rights from
either husband, okay, and you can't remain married to either husband because
you're in a state of married to both. So he sort of
says that these are all consequence of the חידוש chiddush that not
it enables us to do משום עגונה אקילו בה רבנן, mishum agunah
akilu bah rabanan, but it results from משום עגונה אקילו בה רבנן.
mishum agunah akilu bah rabanan. Once we've initiated introduced this idea of
recognizing the second marriage and then the husband shows up, we have
to deal with the consequence of a woman considered literally married to
two people. And therefore when she goes does it שלא ברשות בית
דין, she'lo birshut Beis Din, we never recognize the second marriage. We
never recognize the second marriage, so it's a woman that slept with
another man, nobody recognized that as a marriage, she just slept with
another man, she did it thinking her husband was dead so she's
not a she's somewhat of an אנוסה anusah like רש״י Rashi says
because she didn't willfully commit adultery, right? So she goes back to
her first husband because we never recognized the second marriage. So it's
a brilliant explanation which keeps the meaning of ברשות birshut and שלא
ברשות she'lo birshut the normal way and also makes it a little
bit a little bit more understandable. Look, the woman is still נבך,
nebach, she you know suffers all of this, but at least it's
not like we're punishing her, you know, at least it's somehow it's
just well that's the necessary cost of doing business.
Two questions. One is, her first marriage she just could have gotten
two עדים, edim, right? Yeah. And then it's no more or less
official than her second marriage if she doesn't get two עדים, edim,
so like you know I mean if she just gets two עדים
edim doesn't go to the בית דין. Beis Din. So meaning like
she gets married the same way as the first...
no, no, no, you need to bring evidence, you can't have a
second marriage after your first marriage hasn't... yeah, exactly.
Okay, but the other question is then if that's so true then
why didn't the גמרא Gemara just go that way?
You know, what what... so that's an interesting question, what sort of...
if that's the פשט pshat what led the סתם משנה Stam Mishnah
not to adopt that, the סתם גמרא Stam Gemara not to adopt
that? So I'll say a little bit about that in a minute.
We never really know, after that point it's speculation, yes.
Wouldn't you expect the משנה Mishnah to say she should תצא מזה
ומזה, tetzei mizeh u'mizeh, right?
Right, so again that's the question. Okay, so she's married to two,
so get out
of
one. But again, you know, I think that's all. You have to
connect some not obvious dots. It's in general I think a better
approach. Yes, but whatever.
Do we have the ruling in our day that if a woman
sleeps with another man then her first marriage is annulled?
Not annulled, but she has to get a divorce. She has to
get a divorce. Yeah.
So in this case though, so at what point did that become
a rule as opposed to the idea here that you were saying?
Well, it's not annulled, we're saying she has to get a divorce
from both. תצא מזה ומזה Tetzay mizeh u-mizeh means with a גט.
get.
Yeah, but you were saying, I thought we were saying if she
didn't go to the to the בית דין. Beit Din.
But because then it's not considered like a willful committing of adultery.
She thought her husband was dead, so it wasn't a willful act
of adultery. So then she can go back to her first husband.
And the second guy was never a marriage. I mean, they did
an act of קידושין, kiddushin, but it was never recognized as a
marriage because legally we still recognize the first husband.
Exactly. So then why should she suffer these consequences if it's considered
in that scenario that it's not willful, it's not a sinful thing,
but she's still...
So according to the סתמא דגמרא stama de-gemara and the way רש"י
Rashi explains it, it's just like, yeah, it's true, we really don't
blame her, but we've got to do this in order to allow
her to marry to in order to back up to bolster the
testimony of the first witness, of the single witness. That's the way
רש"י Rashi explains it. The way Shamma Friedman is explaining it is
that we're not punishing her, but this is a consequence of having
validated the second marriage, that therefore now she's married to two men
and now we have to deal
with When she doesn't go to the בית דין
Beit
Din and it's not validated, right?
We're saying then she can go back to the first husband. Right.
So then she maintains her כתובה ketubah with the first husband and
everything she doesn't suffer. And what happens about the child then, what
is his status?
With the first husband, not a ממזר. mamzer. With the second husband,
so that doesn't matter. That's a ממזר. mamzer. Child born through an
act of adultery even if it was completely unintentional still remains a
ממזר. mamzer. Wait, wait, wait, you already asked a question. Yes.
So that explanation of Shamma Friedman's is very satisfying except for one
thing.
It said it would go by Doctor Friedman. Okay.
Except it's setting up a strong incentive not to deal with a
בית דין, Beit Din, and why would the rabbis want that?
That's
Well, because the end of the משנה mishna points out that
you see, and then it also works well, that the end of
the משנה mishna is pointing out that when she operates based on
the בית דין, Beit Din, even though it has these negative consequences,
she isn't sinning and she doesn't bring a קרבן korban because בית
דין Beit Din ultimately gave her permission, whereas if she had operated
unilaterally she would still have to bring a קרבן. korban. So there
still is that factor. And most people aren't willing, like it's a
societal institution, you know, most people are not going to go ahead
and get married until they've got some בית דין Beit Din backing
them up. Like we're not generally assuming that people are going to
go ahead and unilaterally go ahead and get married even though it
was known that their husband was dead until they can have their
husband like officially ruled, you know, even if their husband hasn't shown
up unless they get him officially ruled as dead. You know, you
don't want to get married in a way that society isn't really
recognizing, you want to work through the courts. But I understand, it's
a good question.
The משנה mishna recognizes it but society doesn't necessarily?
Some people will sometimes go ahead and do that. Yes.
So the consequences are the sort that are laid out here,
the semantics between punishment and consequence.
Yeah, there's not much except you're right. I mean, big deal. So
in one case the rabbis have... it's felt like they're, you know,
that was a natural consequence, they weren't trying to punish her here,
they were trying... either way they're trying to do the right thing,
they're trying to do משום עגונה קילו בה רבנן. mishum aguna kilu
bay rabanan. One version says... But she had permission of the בית
דין.
Beit Din.
Yeah, right. Exactly. No, just like what I was just saying, once
we give you this legal status, you're going to have to deal
with the halakhic implications of that legal status. But you're right, bottom
line is the woman is suffering either way. So whether in one
case you say well the rabbis punished her, and in the other
case you say they didn't punish her but they just had to
deal with the logical implications, either way, even when they punished her
they didn't punish her to be mean to her, they punished her
as the way the גמרא gemara phrases it, משום עגונה קילו בה
רבנן mishum aguna kilu bay rabanan because they thought that was the
only mechanism in order to allow the testimony of the עד אחד.
ed echad. So you're right, I mean from this woman's perspective like
what difference does it make? You know, I think from understanding what
was going on for the rabbis, you know, it's a little bit
better because you do wonder like really they needed to do all
this harsh stuff to create the mechanism to believe her? They couldn't
have come up with some other way without all of this negative
consequences? Whereas the other way you understand that like it wasn't that
they couldn't have the mechanism but they had to deal with the
reality of what they had created. But you're right, I mean I'm
not sure it makes it better, it's just I think maybe a
smoother explanation especially because it doesn't you know twist what the words
in the משנה mishna means when it says, you know, because of
ברשות ושלא ברשות. birshut v'shelo birshut. That those now can mean the
simple sense of what they mean. But yes.
I still have two things. One is I still don't understand why
they go down this route.
Okay, we don't know, but I'll talk about them... yeah.
And then the other is, based on the way the גמרא gemara
did it, you know, the interpretation that one ממזר mamzer route is
מדרבנן, mi-derabanan, but you know, I asked you about that yesterday that
doesn't
seem like... It's weird, in other words, ממזר mamzer is like a
really bad thing. Right. You
know what I mean? And there's no way, perhaps no way of
getting out of it because,
yeah, I mean, either way. Right.
And you know,
we're having, fine, I understand. Yeah, it's like ממזר, mamzer, doesn't really
answer, doesn't really answer, like, still, really, it's still all this negative
stuff. But okay, to me, I get that. Why the גמרא Gemara
went down that route, it's not exactly clear, but let me just
say something, because I want to get actually to learning today's דף,
daf, but let me just say one or two
final things I want to say about this is, okay, so that's
in terms of the setup of the basic פשט pshat of the
משנה. Mishnah. The other thing that's worth recognizing is the way the
אמוראים, Amora'im, not the סתם דגמרא, stam d'Gemara, this gets to Michael's
point, that the סתם דגמרא stam d'Gemara consistently pushes to a very
much more מחמיר machmir read, sees this as a קנס knas which
at least conceptually is being strict and so on, and also in
other ways. So, for example, you see that the אמוראים Amora'im are
constantly trying to come ahead and to potentially limit the הלכה halacha
of the משנה, Mishnah, because when the משנה Mishnah is so strict
and
so sweeping, so for example, רב Rav says something which seems completely
radical, which is if there are two witnesses, even if the husband
shows up, she doesn't have, she can stay with the second guy.
So the גמרא Gemara of course, I remember these movies like this,
when a woman gets remarried and the guy comes back and whatever.
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara of course can't deal with that position,
because how could it be the guy is standing in front of
you and you're staying married to the second guy? So it makes
an issue that we don't recognize the first guy, and there's
a question about what witnesses are claiming he's the husband and other
witnesses are claiming the husband is dead, and sort of tones it
down that way. Nevertheless, תוספות Tosafot already points out, like, why shouldn't
we believe the two witnesses? We always say we believe two witnesses,
even against a hundred witnesses. Two witnesses testify something, they're as good
as a hundred. So, so what if the guy is there and
everybody in the town thinks it's the same guy? They'll be just
like a hundred witnesses, and a hundred against two, it evens out,
you know. You always sort of say, something is so patently obvious,
you can't ignore what
the witnesses are saying. Nevertheless, ירושלמי Yerushalmi basically reads רב's Rav's statement
כפשוטו. k'pshuto. It says yes, we say he's not the guy. He
looks like the guy, he talks like the guy, he's got the
same fingerprints as the guy, and nevertheless, we create essentially a legal
fiction and we say the witnesses say he's dead, so you're dead.
You're not the guy. Yes, we live in that world of a
legal fiction. So basically, it creates this radical legal fiction as a
way of avoiding, once that's true, anytime it's based on two witnesses,
you're free from all of the consequences of the משנה. Mishnah. Right?
You're free from all the consequences of the משנה, Mishnah, because even
if the guy shows up, you can stay married to the second
guy. As opposed to what we would say, we'd say if there
were two witnesses, she goes back to the first. Here it's saying,
two witnesses, just stay with the situation. So that's number one, to
appreciate what רב Rav is trying to do and how that would
limit the משנה. Mishnah. And then שמואל Shmuel comes along and שמואל
Shmuel says when she contradicts him, she also doesn't have to go
back. Now the גמרא Gemara reads contradicts him in a similar context
as רב, Rav, that basically there's a question if this is the
guy or not the guy, and there's one witness saying it is,
and or two witnesses, two women, and she says it isn't with
עד אחד, ed echad, and this whole question about whether or not
he's the guy or not. But again, if you read שמואל Shmuel
כפשוטו, k'pshuto, שמואל Shmuel is just saying she just contradicts, witnesses come,
the guy comes up and says he's alive, maybe we wouldn't go
as strong as רב Rav and
say with two witnesses, but maybe she says you're not the guy,
or some broader sense about whenever she denies it, like she claims
it's not the case. Maybe we believe as a, within רב Rav
and שמואל, Shmuel, you get these ways of again trying to limit
the scope of the משנה. Mishnah. But the סתם stam constantly pushes
against that and constantly sort of wants to, rather than limit the
scope of the משנה, Mishnah, limit the statement of רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel and winds up always with all these consequences are always
going to apply as opposed to these attempts to try to limit
it. So you both have the פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah
which is much of a fining and as a קנס. knas. You
also
have the statements of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel which are trying
to limit it, and then you have the סתם דגמרא stam d'Gemara
which is basically much more sort of sweeping in its approach and
pushing off those types of limits. So that's just an appreciation of
some of the dynamics of what's going on here in the גמרא.
Gemara. What we're now in the middle of, finally we'll get to,
is the big סוגיא sugya about יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור דבר
מן התורה. yesh koach be-yad chachamim la'akor davar min ha-Torah. Now the
way the גמרא Gemara introduces this idea of יש כח ביד חכמים
לעקור דבר מן התורה, yesh koach be-yad chachamim la'akor davar min ha-Torah,
why is this brought in in our discussion? What was the גמרא
Gemara seeing as a כח לעקור דבר מן התורה?
koach la'akor davar
min ha-Torah? Do you remember? You learned yesterday. Why was this seen,
what's going on in our משנה? Mishnah? ממזר, mamzer, letting the ממזר
mamzer marry a ממזרת. mamzeret. To which the גמרא's Gemara's answer is
no, even when they said he's a ממזר, mamzer, they didn't let
her marry a ממזר. mamzer. But of course, the bigger question is
maybe the כח לעקור דבר מן התורה koach la'akor davar min ha-Torah
is to believe the עד אחד. ed echad. Right? So this then
leads to a whole discussion in the ראשונים, Rishonim, why at the
end of the day do we believe in עד אחד? ed echad?
Like, where does that ability come from, if...? you need two witnesses
and there basically are three answers in the ראשונים. Rishonim. Okay, answer
number one is יש כח לחכמים לעקור דבר מן התורה. yesh koach
l'Chachamim l'akor davar min haTorah. Okay, that's what תוספות Tosafos says, which
would explain a little bit what it's doing here, not just to
deal with the ממזרת, mamzeres, but to deal with the fact that
we're basically letting her remarry based on עד אחד. ed echad. How
about the fact that the גמרא Gemara as we're seeing is not
so clear that יש כח לעקור דבר מן התורה? yesh koach l'akor
davar min haTorah? So תוספות Tosafos says when it is something that
is backed up a little bit, there's a little logic for it,
even if technically it doesn't work, then they can go ahead and
do it. Where did we see that yesterday? Yesterday we saw that
where the גמרא Gemara basically said that this case about a marriage
to a young woman, a קטנה, ketana, right, he can basically he
can be מטמא metameh to her, the כהן, kohen, because it's a
מת מצוה. meis mitzvah. תוספות Tosafos says that's not really a מת
מצוה. meis mitzvah. What? You're telling me when you're the only person
who's the heir and nobody else is, you're a מת מצוה? meis
mitzvah? Then a כהן kohen should be able to be מטמא metameh
to any relative who he's the sole heir to because he's a
מת מצוה. meis mitzvah. תוספות Tosafos says no, it means it's sort
of like a מת מצוה, meis mitzvah, and because it sort of
is, it's not a real עוקר דבר מן התורה oker davar min
haTorah because there's a certain logic to it, because it appears to
be working within the תורה's Torah categories, it doesn't appear to be
violating, it's not עוקר דבר מן התורה. oker davar min haTorah. And
תוספות Tosafos says and that's what's happening with believing in עד אחד,
ed echad, that it's not עוקר דבר מן התורה oker davar min
haTorah because since we say אשה דייקא ומינסבא, isha dayika u-minseba, you
got the one witness, you got her potential ability to investigate, it
creates a sense of a sufficient evidence and therefore, even though it
really does violate תורה Torah rules, because there's some basis for saying
it, it's not considered עוקר דבר מן התורה. oker davar min haTorah.
That's what תוספות Tosafos says. There's a רש"י Rashi that indicates very
similar approach, but it's different because this is limited to an idea
of קידושין. kiddushin. רש"י Rashi says it's because אפקינהו רבנן לקידושין מיניה.
afkinu rabanan l'kiddushin minei. The rabbis could do הפקעת קידושין. hafka'as kiddushin.
The only thing is that they don't do הפקעת קידושין hafka'as kiddushin
when it clearly
is undermining the institution of marriage, when it clearly is just a
magic poof, you're no longer married. They only do הפקעת קידושין hafka'as
kiddushin when they have the phrase I use is a fig leaf,
when it looks like there's a reason why they're no longer married.
So there's a גט, get, but it was a bad גט. get.
The גט get makes so then they
can behind the scenes do הפקעת קידושין hafka'as kiddushin because it looks
like the גט get is operating. So here behind the scenes they
can do הפקעת קידושין hafka'as kiddushin because it looks like there's legitimate
testimony that the husband is dead or there's an עד אחד. ed
echad. So it's similar to תוספות, Tosafos, if there's an appearance, if
there's a mechanism that looks like it can work even if it
can't work, we'll make it work. Why will we make it work?
According to תוספות Tosafos because יש כח לעקור דבר מן התורה, yesh
koach l'akor davar min haTorah, and according to רש"י Rashi because of
הפקעת קידושין. hafka'as kiddushin. That's two explanations how it works to believe
in עד אחד. ed echad. The third explanation is what the הרא"ה
Ra'ah says, which תוספות Tosafos considered and rejected, and he basically said
once you have sufficient circumstantial evidence, then it's like אנן סהדי. anan
sa'adi. It's like there's so much overwhelming evidence, it's like it's self-evident
that he's dead and that does work on a דאורייתא d'Oraisa level.
So the combination of עד אחד ed echad plus her potential ability
to investigate, which most of the time I assume she didn't do,
anyway, that creates it like an אנן סהדי, anan sa'adi, like it's
so obvious. Of course the problem, the reason תוספות Tosafos rejected that
is really? Come on, it's not a real אנן סהדי. anan sa'adi.
But anyway, that's an attempt to say it works on a דאורייתא
d'Oraisa level. And the final thing I should say is that there's
a ספרי Sifrei that says לא יקום עד אחד באיש לכל עון
ולכל חטאת. lo yakum ed echad b'ish l'chol avon u'l'chol chatas. It
says, so לכל עון ולכל חטאת l'chol avon u'l'chol chatas אינו קם,
eno kam, אבל קם הוא בעדות אשה. aval kam hu b'eidus isha.
So that actually tries to link it to a פסוק pasuk in
the תורה Torah to say that there's a biblical basis of saying
you can believe in עד אחד. ed echad. But it is worth
noting that that question, why do we believe in עד אחד ed
echad here, is a huge question and one possibility, serious possibility, יש
כח לעקור דבר, yesh koach l'akor davar, which is the סוגיא sugia
we're in the middle of, although ironically, our גמרא Gemara only asked
it in the context of ממזר mamzer and
ממזרת, mamzeres, did not ask it in the context of the entire
mechanism here of believing the עד אחד. ed echad. Okay, so all
of that is just to catch myself up since I was not
here for the beginning of this פרק perek and it's such an
important פרק, perek, I wanted to lay that foundation.
And the הלכה halacha from
well, yeah, we'll get to that. There's a very important מהרש"א Marsha
you'll remind me if I don't get to at the end of
מסכת יבמות Masechet Yevamos that deals
with the power of חכמים Chachamim to create these innovations for the
sake of שלום בית shalom bayis and for the sake of משום
עגונה, mishum agunah, yeah, it's perfect for this here, yes.
I don't know if you want to suggest this now, but this
is a kind of contemporary עגונה agunah question, but my impression is
that the cases of missing persons are dealt with a lot more
creatively, shall we say, or proactively than cases
of withholding a גט.
get. It's a very good point and maybe it's because I had
never thought about it that way, but you're right. Meaning in the
aftermath of 9/11, the aftermath of the Holocaust,
but the aftermath of 9/11, there are very creative ways of saying,
oh, there's sufficient evidence that the husband is dead and you can
go ahead. go ahead and remarry, more than the case by the
withholding of a גט. get. And a lot of that might have
to do with the precedent of this פרק, perek, which is all
about set the principle that you can deal with very thin amount
of evidence to base that assumption on, so it's I guess it's
more well-established than the type of mechanisms people are trying to use
for the גט get issue, but it's an interesting question, are there
other reasons as well? That's a very good point way of framing
that. Yeah, because people quote of course משום עגונה אקילו בה רבנן
Mishum agunah akilu bah rabanan for גט get purposes, and it is
sometimes used for גט get purposes, but the real sort of the
breathtaking application of that is what goes on in this פרק, perek,
meaning once you get over the negative consequence if the guy shows
up, we still have to appreciate how breathtaking it is that חז״ל
Chazal believed such weak evidence to allow the woman to get remarried.
There's a whole nice book out by the way, and he's not
here to create problems and to contradict, which is also very important.
And there's a book out that was after which was a collection
of the various תשובות teshuvot that were given at the aftermath of
9/11 in terms of letting women remarry. I forget what the name
of it was, but if I can find I'll let you know.
I just the other day saw the final, my god, installment of
the Hobbit with the kids, oh my god, how they turned one
tiny little book into three two and a half hour movies. Anyway,
but the last scene was that
Bilbo Baggins comes back and they're auctioning off all of his stuff
because he was gone for 10 months or whatever, 30 months he
was presumed dead. So it was exactly this, okay who cares you
shut up you're still dead! So anyway, all right, let's leave that
anyway.
So דף צ״ה עמוד א׳ Daf Tzadi Hey Amud Aleph actually turns
to today's דף. daf.
Okay, תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here, first line in צ״ה
עמוד א׳. Tzadi Hey Amud Aleph. אכל תרומה טמאה ומשלם חולין טהורים.
Achal terumah temeiah u'meshalem chullin tehorim. The הלכה halacha is that if
somebody eats תרומה, terumah, a non-כהן kohen בשוגג, be'shogeg, he pays back
the same amount of food to the כהן kohen and that food
becomes תרומה terumah in its stead. Now what if it is תרומה
טמאה? terumah temeiah? He also has to pay it back. So it
says he should pay back טהור חולין tahor chullin because then at
least the כהן kohen will get טהור תרומה, tahor terumah, which would
be better.
שישלם חולין טמאין, She'yeshalem chullin temei'in, if he pays חולין טמאין, chullin
temei'in, סומכוס אומר משום רבי מאיר בשוגג תשלומו תשלומין. Sumchus omer mishum
Rabi Meir be'shogeg tashlumo tashlumin. If he unintentionally gave
טמא חולין, tamei chullin, he wanted to give טהור tahor but he
gave טמא, tamei, then fine, then it's a good paying back. במזיד
אין
תשלומו תשלומין.
Be'mezid ein
tashlumo tashlumin.
If he intentionally did it, it doesn't count and presumably he has
to give טהור tahor in its stead and this is nothing. וחכמים
אומרים אחד זה ואחד זה תשלומו תשלומין. Ve'chachamim omrim echad zeh ve'echad
zeh tashlumo tashlumin. Either way it counts and the כהן kohen pockets
what he gave, the טמא חולין tamei chullin which became תרומה. terumah.
וחוזר ומשלם חולין טהורים. Ve'chozer u'meshalem chullin tehorim.
But then we make him give a second time חולין טהורים. chullin
tehorim. Okay, yeah,
like exactly, we want the כהן kohen to get the חולין טהור,
chullin tahor, but yeah, it's similar to before, the תרומה terumah is
תרומה terumah but he does וחוזר וטהור, ve'chozer ve'tahor, like וחזר ויתרום
ve'chozar ve'yitrom like the גמרא Gemara said before. Okay, ואבינא בה, Ve'avina
bah, we asked on this: במזיד אין תשלומו תשלומין, Be'mezid ein tashlumo
tashlumin, even if he intentionally gives טמא חולין, tamei chullin, why is
it not good? תבוא עליו ברכה. Tavo alav berachah. He should be
blessed! Why? דאכל מיניה מידי דלא חזי ליה בימי טומאתו. De'achal minei
midi de'la chazi leh bi'ymei tumato. He ate something the כהן kohen
could not eat when he was טמא, tamei, because
he ate תרומה טמאה, terumah temeiah, which you have no use for
other than burning it. תרומה
טמאה, Terumah temeiah, excuse me, I said חולין. chullin. תרומה טמאה Terumah
temeiah which he had no use for it. וקמשלם מידי דחזי ליה
בימי טומאתו. U'kameshalem midi de'chazi leh bi'ymei tumato. And he gave him
חולין טמאין. chullin temei'in. And חולין טמאין chullin temei'in a כהן kohen
is allowed to eat when he's טמא. tamei. I mean maybe he
can't eat when he's טהור, tahor, it'll make him טמא tamei or
whatever, but anyway, a כהן kohen can eat it. So he did
a good thing if he gave טמא חולין, tamei chullin, it's better
than giving טמא תרומה, tamei terumah, thank you, טמא חולין, tamei chullin,
right? Actually, and also you also have to say, right.
So why is that not an acceptable thing? Now of course, it
sounds like that the טמא חולין tamei chullin doesn't become תרומה, terumah,
but the evidence is that even when he gives the טמא חולין,
tamei chullin, it does become תרומה. terumah. So he didn't really make
him any better. He ate תרומה טמאה terumah temeiah and he gave
him תרומה טמאה. terumah temeiah. What's the
that's the תורת ההלכה. Toras halacha. That's the הלכה. halacha. When you
pay back תשלומי תרומה tashlumei terumah it becomes תרומה. terumah. Anyway,
so how does it really make it any better? So תוספות Tosafot
says, okay, it doesn't really make it any better, but תוספות Tosafot
says, where's
תוספות? Tosafot?
So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, second wide line of the
תוספות, Tosafot, where it says אף על גב, Af al gav, the
third word: אף על גב דכי משלם חולין טמאין נעשו תרומה טמאה,
מכל מקום תבוא עליו ברכה דנפטר הוא שמשלם יותר ממה שהפסיד לכהן
Af al gav de'chi meshalem chullin temei'in na'asu terumah temei'ah, mikol makom
tavo alav berachah de'niftar hu she'meshalem yoter mimah she'hifsid la'kohen because he
gave the כהן kohen חולין טמאין chullin temei'in that was at least
worth more than תרומה טמאה. terumah temei'ah. חולין טמאין, chullin temei'in, so
even though from the כהן's kohen perspective,
תרומה טמאה terumah temei'ah was taken from him and he got back
חולין טמאין chullin temei'in which became תרומה טמאה, terumah temei'ah, but at
least this guy, he paid something חולין טמאין chullin temei'in is worth
more because תרומה טמאה terumah temei'ah you can't even eat, you have
to burn. So this guy at least paid more out of pocket
than what he took. So why is So bad? Big deal! He
ate חולין טמאים, Chullin Tmeiyim, he gave him, he actually, I get,
he ate תרומה טמאה, Truma Tmeah, he gave him חולין טמאים. Chullin
Tmeiyim. What's so bad? The guy paid more out of pocket than
what he took. The כהן Kohen got back what he lost. Why
are we saying that it's a big deal?
So תוספות Tosafot deals with that issue which I'm not going to
get into. So what's the big deal? So the גמרא Gemara says
ואמר רבה ואיתימא כדי. Va'amar Rava Ve'itima Kadi.
רבה Rava says and some say it was said anonymously, חסורי מחסרא
והכי קתני, Chassori Mechessra Ve'hachi Katni,
that really
this משנה Mishna is missing some words, or ברייתא Braita is, here's
how the ברייתא Braita has to be read. והכי קתני, Ve'hachi Katni,
אכל תרומה טמאה משלם כל דהו. Achal Truma Tmeah Meshaleim Kol Dehu.
If he ate תרומה טמאה, Truma Tmeah, he can pay back anything,
meaning even חולין טמאים. Chullin Tmeiyim. Why not? You ate תרומה טמאה,
Truma Tmeah, you pay back טמאים. Tmeiyim. That's number one. The real
case what's going on in the ברייתא Braita is not eating תרומה
טמאה, Truma Tmeah, where of course you should be able to pay
back חולין טמאים. Chullin Tmeiyim. It's eating תרומה טהורה. Truma Tehora. Here's
what it's talking about. אכל תרומה טהורה, Achal Truma Tehora, if you
ate תרומה טהורה, Truma Tehora, then you ate something that was טהור
Tahor that the כהן Kohen was allowed to eat. You better give
him back something that's טהור Tahor so he'll be allowed to eat
it. In that case, משלם חולין טהורים. Meshaleim Chullin Tehorim. You have
to give back טהור Tahor חולין. Chullin. שילם חולין
טמאים, Shileim Chullin Tmeiyim, what if you gave back חולין טמאים? Chullin
Tmeiyim? Now you really hurt the כהן, Kohen, because that's going to
become תרומה טמאה. Truma Tmeah. So you ate תרומה טהורה, Truma Tehora,
and instead you're going to give back something that's going to become
תרומה טמאה. Truma Tmeah. So in that case, סומכוס אומר משום רבי
מאיר, Sumchus Omer Mishum Rabbi Meir, סומכוס Sumchus says in the name
of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, בשוגג תשלומו תשלומין במזיד אין תשלומו תשלומין.
Beshogeg Tashlumo Tashlumin Bemezid Ein Tashlumo Tashlumin. בשוגג Beshogeg
it works and you're done, במזיד Bemezid it doesn't work and it
didn't become תרומה Truma at all and you have to go out
and give it again presumably. וחכמים אומרים בין בשוגג בין במזיד תשלומו
תשלומין. Vachachamim Omrim Bein Beshogeg Bein Bemezid Tashlumo Tashlumin.
Either way it works and the כהן Kohen gets what you separated,
וחוזר ומשלם חולין טהורים, Ve'chozer Umeshaleim Chullin Tehorim, but you're going to
have to give again from טהור Tahor תרומה. Truma. So חכמים Chachamim
are of course very strict. What you gave, you gave, and now
you have to do it again. Okay, but of course the קשיא
Kashya is not such a חידוש Chiddush for at least according to
the חכמים, Chachamim, what you did worked and now they're making you
pay a second time. But according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, we
made it not work. How could we make it not work if
דאורייתא De'oraisa it did work? והכא דמדאורייתא תשלומין מעליא הוי. Ve'hacha Demide'oraisa
Tashlumin Mealya Havei.
Here דאורייתא De'oraisa presumably it does work, even when you pay back
טמאים. Tmeiyim. Michael asks a good question that you have to pay
back the same value. So why does it work? So תוספות Tosafot
says well maybe you pay back a lot more, so it is
the same value, but nevertheless you gave him חולין טמאים. Chullin Tmeiyim.
So דאורייתא De'oraisa actually works. But nevertheless, דאי מקדש בה כהן אשה
תפסו לה קידושין, De'i Mekadesh Bah Kohen Isha Tafsu Lah Kiddushin,
that now this money that initially you gave, this חולין טמאים, Chullin
Tmeiyim, the כהן Kohen דאורייתא De'oraisa owns, and the big consequence of
owning that money is that now he can marry a woman with
it and she'll be his
wife. ואמרו רבנן אין תשלומו תשלומין, Ve'amru Rabbanan Ein Tashlumo Tashlumin, that
if you did it במזיד Bemezid according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
it didn't take place at all and that stuff doesn't really belong
to the כהן, Kohen, it really belongs to you. Therefore, let's say
what happened was you gave the stuff to a כהן, Kohen, and
it was done במזיד, Bemezid, and you gave him this תשלומי תרומה,
Tashlumei Truma, and he went ahead and he married a woman with
it. And then he's going to say, what? It was במזיד? Bemezid?
Okay, forget it, that didn't work. Take all your money back, take
it all back, you have to give me a second time, and
this woman isn't married to me because I married her with money
that wasn't mine. But that's not true, דאורייתא De'oraisa it actually was
his money. So why should we, right? So how can we go
ahead and make it not work if דאורייתא De'oraisa it does work?
ואמרו רבנן אין תשלומו תשלומין וקשרינן אשת איש לעלמא. Ve'amru Rabbanan Ein
Tashlumo Tashlumin Vekashrinan Eishet Ish Le'alma.
We're going to say that payment, when it was done, you know,
of the
חולין טמאים, Chullin Tmeiyim, didn't work at all and it didn't belong
to the כהן. Kohen. And therefore the woman isn't married. So how
can we allow this big דאורייתא De'oraisa consequence in something that you
know, דאורייתא De'oraisa really worked just because we don't like the fact
that he hurt the כהן? Kohen? אלא לאו, Ela Lav, so you
see that יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור דבר מן התורה, Yesh Koach
Beyad Chachamim La'akor Davar Min HaTorah, that we can do that. הגמרא
Hagemara says no. מאי אין תשלומו תשלומין דקאמר רבי מאיר דמהדר ובעי
למיהדר שלומי חולין טהורין. Mai Ein Tashlumo Tashlumin Dekamar Rabbi Meir Demehadar
Uva'ei Lemehadar Shlumei Chullin Tehorin. No, what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
not saying is that the כהן Kohen doesn't get what you initially
gave him. You do give it. When he says it didn't work,
it doesn't mean that the first thing didn't become תרומה. Truma. It
means you have to give a second time. Okay, but now one
minute, if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying oh it doesn't work
meaning it worked but you have to give a second time, well
that's what the חכמים Chachamim said. It works and you have to
give a second time. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי סומכוס
היינו רבנן. Ei Hachi Sumchus Hainu Rabbanan.
It's funny how it switches from רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir to סומכוס.
Sumchus. Anyway, they're saying the same thing, they're both saying you have
to give a second time because nobody is saying it didn't work.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא קנסו
שוגג אטו מזיד איכא בינייהו. Amar Rav Acha Brei DeRav Ika Kensu
Shogeg Atu Mezid Ika Beinaiahu. No, the difference is not what happens
when you do it במזיד. Bemezid. When you do it במזיד Bemezid
everybody agrees, it took effect and you have to give it a
second time. The second question is that what happens when you did
it בשוגג. Beshogeg. The חכמים Chachamim say same thing, takes effect and
you give a second time. And there רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
being more lenient and saying no, if you did it בשוגג, Beshogeg,
you don't have to do it the second time, it took effect
and you're done. So the real question is whether you punish him
in a case of שוגג Shogeg to give the second time, but
everybody agrees in all. of the cases what you did took effect,
we're not being עוקר דבר מן התורה. oker davar min ha'Torah. Two
interesting points to point out here, number one is תוספות Tosafot asks
an obvious question, why do you have to have a complicated case
about whether this woman he married with this תרומה terumah will be
his wife or not? Why don't you just say there's a consequence
about like, you know, about what happens if let's say I don't
know, if you consider it to be non-תרומה, terumah, then a כהן,
Kohen, then if a ישראל Yisrael eats it, he's free from the
punishment of eating תרומה, terumah, like if a כהן Kohen eats it
when he's טמא, tamei, he's free from the punishment of eating תרומה.
terumah.
So that's one question, which is interesting why the גמרא Gemara went
there. The other important thing I wanted to point out, because talking
about like a lot of so many דאורייתא De'oraita so many like
ש"ס Shas concepts that are coming up, is תוספות Tosafot asks I
don't understand, if the גמרא Gemara here is only concerned about the
money issue, why didn't it just say הפקר בית דין הפקר? hefker
beit din hefker? Because the גמרא's Gemara question is how could we
say it works that it's now owned by the כהן Kohen if
דאורייתא De'oraita it's not owned by the כהן? Kohen? I'm sorry, how
could we say I'm sorry, how could we say it's not owned
by the כהן, Kohen, right, it didn't work if דאורייתא De'oraita it
is owned by the כהן? Kohen? That's the גמרא's Gemara question, isn't
that עוקר דבר מן התורה? oker davar min ha'Torah? This what's the
big deal, this is all just a question of monetary issues, say
הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beit din hefker. Yes, דאורייתא De'oraita it's
owned by the כהן, Kohen, but we're going to say he doesn't
own it and it didn't take effect, it's all just transferring ownership
of money, right? You learned that yesterday, the principle of הפקר בית
דין הפקר. hefker beit din hefker. So there's a great two words
in תוספות Tosafot that says something. If you look three lines down
in the wide lines, he says, I'm sorry, no, where תוספות Tosafot
says, he says, oh yes, about right before the תוספות Tosafot והא,
ve'ha, you see the תוספות Tosafot והא ve'ha about ten lines down
in the תוספות. Tosafot. Yeah,
so go about right
before the beginning of that word, he says, he says like this:
דהכא אין שייך לומר כן, de'hacha ein shayach lomar kein,
you can't say הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker beit din hefker and
that the כהן Kohen doesn't own it and it doesn't take effect
and we're going to use הפקר בית דין הפקר, hefker beit din
hefker, why? Because דמה פשע כהן שיש לנו להפקיר ממונו. demah pasha
Kohen she'yesh lanu lehafkir mamono. Why, what did the כהן Kohen do
wrong that we should say this money that he owns he doesn't
own? Which is okay, but we're not doing it because he's a
bad guy, we're doing it because this is the mechanism in order
that we say that it didn't take effect. But what this points
out is a very important principle about again, we spoke before about
how the סתם stam of the גמרא Gemara sometimes broaden statements from
their original meaning. הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker beit din hefker in
its original application, certainly in the book of יהושע, Yehoshua, but probably
also in the early application in the גמרא, Gemara, was much more
of a case where we were fining somebody, right? Remember כל אשר
יבא בעצת הזקנים יחרם כל רכושו. kol asher yavo be'atzat ha'zekeinim yacharam
kol rechusho. The פסוקים pesukim we base it on was
if you're not going to show up, then we're going to sort
of fine you and like disown your property, or whatever the word
is, you know sort of seize your property as a result of
a monetary penalty, right? So to say from there that we can
manipulate who owns what, to take a power of fining to a
side of manipulating ownership is not so clear. And תוספות Tosafot here
says something that is much more in line with the original idea
of fining somebody, that we're not going to do הפקר בית דין
הפקר hefker beit din hefker unless you actually
did something wrong. If you didn't do anything wrong, we're not going
to be able to use the mechanism of הפקר בית דין הפקר,
hefker beit din hefker, which is a brilliant idea that gets it
much closer to its original root in an idea of fining rather
than just an idea of manipulating ownership of property.
Yes, depends which side you're looking at that. I mean you're looking
at the guy who paid, he did do something wrong,
you're looking at the כהן, Kohen, he didn't do anything wrong.
Right, but we're taking away the כהן's Kohen money. We're not going
to take away... what? Alright, but that initial act of taking away
the money, you're right, so that's the חידוש chiddush of תוספות.
Tosafot. Alright, הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker beit din hefker I always
felt was like a way to keep an orderly society. Yes, and
in that sense you can understand the פסוק pasuk in יהושע Yehoshua
that way as well, sure, because it looks like a punishment but
it also looks like, you know, we want to have local ownership
of land and things like that.
Right, so that's presumably how the גמרא Gemara winds up understanding it
in that broader sense.
You have an objection about the fine, you don't buy it?
Interesting. I think you've internalized a lot of how the גמרא Gemara
uses הפקר בית דין הפקר, hefker beit din hefker, but if you
sort of start at the opposite direction and see the פסוקים pesukim
and see the original statements of the אמוראים Amoraim and then see
where it gets to later, it seems that there is a progression
of that idea. In the end it does
work, but anyway. Alright, moving on. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, תא
שמע, ta shema, דם שנטמא
וזרקו בשוגג הורצה במזיד לא הורצה. dam she'nitma ve'zarko beshogeg hurtza bemeizid
lo hurtza. So you have blood of a קרבן korban that became
טמא, tamei, you're not supposed to put it on the מזבח, mizbeiach,
but you go ahead and you do it. Now if you do
it בדיעבד be'diavad it works because that's the whole thing that the
ציץ Tzitz מרצה על עוון הקדשים mirtzeh al avon ha'kodashim when קרבנות
korbanot become טמא, tamei, the ציץ Tzitz says that בדיעבד be'diavad it'll
work if you were זורק zorek the דם, dam, but you're not
supposed to. So if you did it בשוגג, be'shogeg, you get כפרה.
kaparah. If you did it במזיד, be'meizid, the כהן Kohen did it
במזיד, be'meizid, the בעלים be'alim don't get כפרה. kaparah. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so what does it mean they don't get... כפרה *kappara*.
If you don't get כפרה *kappara*, what do you have to do
as the owner? Bring another קרבן korban *korban*. But if דאורייתא de-oraisa
*de'oraisa* you are יוצא *yotzei*, how could you bring another קרבן korban.
*korban* if it's let's say a חטאת *chatas*, סו *so* no, or
שלמים *shlamim*? That's one thing, but if it's a חטאת *chatas*, it's
חולין בעזרה *chullin ba'azarah*. והכא דמדאורייתא ציץ מרצה *vehacha demide'oraisa tzitz meratzeh*,
here biblically you get כפרה *kappara*, דתניא על מה הציץ מרצה *detanya
al mah hatzitz meratzeh*, what does the ציץ *tzitz* cause for it
to be, meaning from the word רצו *ritzo*, like וירצה *veyeratzeh*, you
know, desired by God, but meaning it's a technical term that the
קרבן korban. *korban* is valid? על הדם ועל הבשר ועל החלב שנטמא
*al hadam ve'al habasar ve'al hachelev shenitma*, whether the blood and the
meat and the fat that became טמא *tamei*, בין בשוגג בין במזיד
בין באונס בין ברצון *bein beshogeg bein bemayzid bein be'ones bein beratzon*,
whether intentional or unintentional, willful or unwillful, or unwillful-willful, בין ביחיד בין
בציבור *bein beyachid bein betzibbur*, whether it's a קרבן יחיד *korban yachid*
קרבן ציבור *korban tzibbur*. So in all cases. ואמרי רבנן לא הורצה
*ve'amri rabanan lo urtza*, but the rabbis say if you did we
don't want you to do it, and if you did it במזיד
*bemayzid*, we're not going to let you benefit from it. We're not
going to say it, we're going to say it doesn't work. וקא
הדר מייתו חולין בעזרה *vekadar maito chullin ba'azarah*, and then you're bringing
חולין בעזרה *chullin ba'azarah*, so you see יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור
דבר מן התורה yesh koach beyad chachamim la'akor davar min hatorah. *yeish
koach beyad chachamim la'akor davar min hatorah*. סו אמר רבי יוסי בר
חנינא מאי לא הורצה דקאמר להתר בשר באכילה *so amar Rabi Yose
bar Chanina mai lo urtza dekama lehater basar ba'achila*. No, it doesn't
mean that you bring another קרבן *korban*. No, you got כפרה *kappara*.
What does it mean לא הורצה *lo urtza*? That you don't get
to eat the meat. Okay, or the כהנים kohanim
*kohanim* don't get to eat it, which by the way works better
because it's the כהן *kohein* who's being the מזיד *mayzid* about being
זורק *zorek* the דם *dam*. So it should be better that it's
the כהן *kohein* who suffers the consequences.
So the כהן *kohein* doesn't and the כהנים *kohanim* are the ones
who eat the חטאת *chatas*. אבל בעלים be'alim נתכפרו *aval be'alim niskappru*,
but the owners get כפרה *kappara*. So therefore it's not עקירה דבר
מן התורה *akira davar min hatorah*. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says
סוף סוף קא מסתקר אכילת בשר *sof sof kamis'akar achilas basar*, okay,
so you're not bringing חולין בעזרה *chullin ba'azarah*, but you're uprooting the
מצווה *mitzvah* to eat the meat of a קרבן *korban*. וכתיב *vekasiv*
and the verse says ואכלו אותם אשר כופר בהם *ve'achalu osam asher
kuppar bahem*, it they should eat it those that are atoned by
it, or are anyway funny פסוק *pasuk*, but anyway it means that
the כהנים *kohanim* eat it. מלמד שהכהנים אוכלים ובעלים מתכפרים *milamed shehakohanim
ochlim ube'alim miskapprim*, they eat it אשר כופר בהם *asher kuppar bahem*,
through which they the owners get atonement. So the כהנים *kohanim* eat
it and the owners get atonement. So anyway and you're here not
doing the מצווה *mitzvah* of eating the meat. אמר ליה שב ואל
תעשה shev ve-al ta'aseh, שאני *amar lei shev ve'al ta'aseh shani*. Yeah,
that's עוקר דבר oker davar מן התורה *okair davar min hatorah*, but
it's עוקר דבר *okair davar* by saying don't do something. We're not
actively being עוקר *okair*, we're just telling you to sit on your
תחת *tuchus* and וממילא *umimmila* something won't get done properly, but we're
not actively you know making a married woman unmarried or we're not
making you eat תרומה *terumah*, you know, eat something that's תרומה *terumah*
that isn't תרומה *terumah*, I mean eat something that is whatever that's
you know treat something that's תרומה *terumah* like it's not תרומה *terumah*.
We're just telling you sit, don't do something. That nobody disagrees that
the חכמים chachamim *chachamim* have the ability and that you will often
hear the phrase יש כח yesh koach, לעקור דבר מן התורה בשב
ואל תעשה be-shev ve-al ta'aseh *yeish koach la'akor davar min hatorah beshev
ve'al ta'aseh*. Okay, that is what emerges from this סוגיא sugya. *suggya*,
meaning the idea was always there, but the those words יש כח
yesh koach לעקור בשב ואל תעשה *yeish koach la'akor beshev ve'al ta'aseh*
framing it that way is what is the conclusion here of this
גמרא gemara *Gemara*. By the way, it should be noted, it doesn't
just mean that you're only not doing an עשה *aseh*, you know,
as opposed to being עובר *over* on a לאו *lav*, because here
actually there's a לאו *lav* about לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר *lo
sosiru mimmenu ad boker*, right there is a לאו *lav* of נותר
*nosar*, but what you're doing is you're just passively not doing the
right thing as opposed to actively going ahead and that חכמים chachamim
*chachamim* actually that we have to concede they do have the ability
to say that. Just one minute. אמר ליה *amar lei*, he said
back to him, בעינא לאותביך *ba'ilah osivach*, I was going to ask
you a whole list of questions I was ready to prove that
יש כח koach, לעקור דבר מן התורה *yeish koach la'akor davar min
hatorah*, here are they: ערל *arel*, if somebody is an ערל *arel*
which is actually specifically means that that let's say somebody got a
ברית מילה *bris milah* they have to, but specifically also is dealing
with a consequence of a of a גר *geir* a מעובל *me'ovel*
a convert who converted and it's right before פסח *pesach*. The הלכה
halacha *halacha* is we treat it like he just separated from a
dead body and he needs a seven-day process of טהרה *taharah*, even
though דאורייתא de-oraisa *de'oraisa* that's not required. But by rabbinically requiring that
he's not going to be able to bring a קרבן פסח *korban
pesach* which is a huge מצווה *mitzvah* and we're going to tell
him don't bring a קרבן פסח *korban pesach*. That's ערל *arel*. הזאה
*haza'ah*, somebody needs the final sprinkling of the ashes of, right right
right, he says I was about to ask you these questions. הזאה
*haza'ah* sprinkling the ashes of פרה אדומה *parah adumah*, it's guy's day
number seven, it's ערב פסח *erev pesach*, it's שבת shabbos, *shabbos*. If
you would let us do the sprinkling he could go ahead and
have the קרבן פסח *korban pesach* brought and eat it that night.
Because you won't let us sprinkle on the guy on שבת shabbos.
*shabbos* because that's an איסור דרבנן *issur d'rabbanan* of sprinkling on שבת
Shabbos, *shabbos*, right then therefore the guy's not going to be able
to bring קרבן פסח *korban pesach* and you're going to be עוקר
*okair* his bringing of the קרבן פסח *korban pesach*. ואיזמל *ve'izmel*, bringing
a knife of the
the scalpel for ברית מילה *bris milah*, if we forgot to have
it ready ahead of time, you can't even bring it through a
כרמלית דרבנן *karmelis d'rabbanan* a rabbinic רשות *reshus* and by because of
the rabbinic idea of carrying in that type of a place we're
not going to be able to do the ברית מילה *bris milah*
today. סדין בציצית *sadin betzitzis*, if you have a linen garment we
tell you don't wear ציצית tzitzit *tzitzis* on a linen garment. Why?
Because you'll come to wear it at night and it will be
שעטנז *shatnez* because the blue string is wool, has to be wool
and it's and it's you know wool and linen שעטנז *shatnez* which
you're allowed to do when you're doing the מצווה *mitzvah* of ציצית
tzitzit *tzitzis*, but because we're concerned that you will go ahead and
wear it at night when it's not the time of the מצווה
*mitzvah* and you'll be wearing שעטנז *shatnez* when you're not doing the
מצווה *mitzvah*, we tell you don't. put on ציצית tzitzit at all
and there you are violating the מצוה mitzvah of having ציצית tzitzit
on your garment. Okay, וכבשי עצרת vekivsei atzeret
and the lambs of שבועות, shavuot, רש״י Rashi says it's not a
exactly clear what this means but רש״י Rashi says here's what I
think it means, basically if somebody שחט shechted the two כבשים kvasim
that you bring on שבועות, shavuot, שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, the הלכה
halacha is, the דאורייתא de-oraisa. הלכה is is that you sprinkle the
blood and you go ahead and eat the meat like any קרבן
that's brought
שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, but if it's שבועות shavuot it happens to
be on שבת, we say don't sprinkle the blood. Okay, and therefore
by not sprinkling the blood you're not going to be eating the
meat of this קרבן. Okay, so that's another thing by passively you're
not doing the מצוה mitzvah the way you're supposed to. ושופר ולולב,
veshofar velulav, we don't take שופר shofar and take לולב lulav on
שבת. All these things that you are not doing דאורייתא de'oraisa מצוות,
mitzvos, I was going to bring all these things as proofs that
יש כח ביד חכמים. yesh koach beyad chachamim. השתא דשנית לן שבו
ואל תעשה, hashta deshanit lan shev veal ta'aseh, now that you said
oh when you're just passive it's not a question that I concede.
So לאו מעקר הוא, lo me-akar hu, so it's not really like
you're actively uprooting. כולם נמי שבו ואל תעשה נינהו kulam nami shev
veal ta'aseh ninhu and all of these are passive, so there goes
all my questions. But what we have established is the חכמים chachamim.
do have the ability, one minute in a case of שבו ואל
תעשה. shev veal ta'aseh. Let's just do one more and then I'll
take the questions. תא שמע, ta shema, אליו תשמעון, elav tishme'un, you
should listen to a
נביא. navi. Even if a נביא navi tells you to violate one
of the מצוות mitzvos in the תורה, Torah, like אליהו בהר הכרמל
Eliyahu behar hakarmel when אליהו Eliyahu had them build an altar בהר
הכרמל behar hakarmel which is building a במה bamah even in the
time of a בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, הכל לפי שעה, hakol lefi
sha'ah, anything which is an exigent circumstances, שמע לו, shma lo, listen
to him. So you see you can override a דאורייתא. Okay now
of course that was just a one-time thing, לפי שעה, lefi sha'ah,
it wasn't a permanent change of the system. Also he wasn't exactly
חכמים but anyway, the גמרא gemara says no, שאני התם דכתיב אליו
תשמעון. shani hatam dechtiv elav tishme'un. No, it's there's a special מצוה
mitzvah to listen to a נביא, navi, that's about a נביא, navi,
it's not about חכמים. ומיגמר מיניה, u-migmar minei, okay but let's learn
from it that if the נביא navi has the ability חז״ל chazal
have the ability. And now the גמרא gemara says again exactly interesting
גמרא gemara of assuming we can learn from a נביא navi to
חז״ל, chazal, and the גמרא gemara says no, מיגדר מילתא שאני, migdar
milta shani, there it was for protecting a thing, meaning it was
like an exigent circumstance. Things should be done for a brief period
of time for an exigent circumstance is very different than being עוקר
דבר you know
systematically within the legal system, within the legal system it was הוראת
שעה. hora'at sha'ah. Okay, there was a Charlie you had a question?
Well yeah the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi seems to think that it's biblically prohibited to blow שופר
shofar on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
Yes, that is true. Any other questions with that before? Yes.
Is it did it say they
do
not eat the meat just being by being passive? Correct. And does
that person still receive atonement? Yes.
Yes. So and he doesn't bring another קרבן. Okay, yes, when it
says the כהנים eat the meat and the בעלים be'alim are atoned
for, that means ideally but even if they don't eat the meat
the בעלים still are atoned for. Now I want to say two
important two interesting things, then we'll still hopefully get even a little
further. One is תוספות Tosafot asks what do you mean ציצית tzitzit.
is שבו ואל תעשה? shev veal ta'aseh? ציצית tzitzit if you're wearing
your four-cornered garment and not putting on ציצית tzitzit that's קום ועשה,
kum ve'aseh, you're doing an active act of wearing without putting on
ציצית. tzitzit So תוספות Tosafot asks an interesting question of what conceptually
is the מצוה? mitzvah? תוספות Tosafot says the putting on isn't yet
the obligation, the obligation is once it's on you to put on
and therefore he says so it's not that by putting on I
was I was violating the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית tzitzit because the
moment of putting on is not yet the obligation, the obligation is
once it's on and once it's on I'm only passively not wearing
it and it's not considered I'm only passively not putting on ציצית
and it's not a violation that I'm wearing the בגד, beged, the
violation is that I'm not putting on ציצית on a בגד beged
that I am passively
wearing. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot asks an interesting question of how do you
conceptualize the מצוות mitzvos and a מצוה mitzvah on the garment, a
מצוה mitzvah on the person, fascinating discussions in terms of ציצית the
idea that the גמרא gemara. frames this as passive rather than active.
The other interesting thing is about the whole issue of the נביא
navi and what the גמרא Gemara was thinking
and you know so תוספות Tosafot says I don't understand if God
told the נביא navi to do this the reason you're doing it
is not because he has the כח, the reason you're doing it
is because God said so. But God wouldn't but God wouldn't have
said to listen to him when he God tells him to do
that unless it was that was all a legal principle that you're
allowed to sort of listen you know in certain circumstances to violate
the rules. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot has other interesting questions about about you
know the comparison of the נביא navi to חז״ל chazal here. Okay,
so anyway let's go on let's read another case of the גמרא.
Gemara תא שמע, ta shema, ביטלו מבוטל, bitlo mevutal, דברי רבי. divrei
Rabbi.
So here we get to a classic case beginning of of not
the beginning excuse me, the I think fourth פרק perek of גיטין
Gittin where it says that a person sends a שליח shaliach to
deliver a גט get to his wife, he's allowed to annul the
שליח shaliach the גט get not in the שליח's shaliach presence, if
he makes a בית דין beis din he can annul the גט.
get. Problem is that then the שליח shaliach doesn't know about it,
delivers the גט get to the wife, the woman thinks she's divorced,
remarries, and in the end the whole גט get is is void
and he can basically get his wife, a kid, a ממזר mamzer
there, and get his wife all messed up. So the Rabbis said
you're not allowed to annul the גט get not in the presence
of the woman or the שליח. shaliach. Okay, it sounds very nice.
Not allowed. Let's say he went ahead and he did it anyway.
So there's a debate, if he was מבטל mevatel the גט get
not in the wife's presence, does it work or not? So בטלו,
bitlo, if he annulled it not in the wife's presence and violated
the rabbinic rule, מבוטל, mevutal, it is annulled. דברי רבי. divrei Rebbi.
So the, it goes, it still works, you know, even though we
didn't want him to do it, it'll work. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר איני יכול לבטלו ולא להוסיף על תנאו, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer eini yachol levatlo velo lehosif al tna'o, if it's not in
the woman's or the שליח's shaliach presence, he cannot annul the גט
get and he cannot add to some stipulation on the גט, get,
and if he does, it does not work. שאם כן מה כח
בית דין יפה she'im kein mah koach beis din yafeh because if
you think that he can, what good is it what we're trying
to do? We're trying to stop this from happening and he's just
gonna go like, okay, I didn't listen to you, I did it
anyway. No, so we have to back up our rule and to
protect the woman, we're basically going to prevent it from working even
בדיעבד. bedi'eved.
So this sounds like יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור דבר. yesh koach
beyad chachamim la'akor davar. We're going to back it up and say
it doesn't work. So the גמרא Gemara says, והכא דמדאורייתא בטל גט,
vehacha demide'oraisa batel get,
here biblically the גט get is בטל, batel, ומשום מה כח בית
דין יפה מה כח בית דין קשרינן אשת איש לעלמא, umishum mah
koach beis din yafeh mah koach beis din kashreina eishes ish le'alma,
and in order to back up the powers בית דין, beis din,
we're allowing this woman who is still biblically married, because the גט
get is בטל, batel, and we're saying that she's divorced. So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, קשרינן אשת, kashreina eishes, so מן דמקדש אדעתא
דרבנן מקדש ואפקעינהו רבנן לקידושין. man de'mekadesh ada'ata derabbanan mekadesh afkinu rabbanan
lekiddushin. No,
it's not based on יש כח ביד חכמים, yesh koach beyad chachamim,
it's based on a special area where they are able to, not
a sweeping ability to עקור דבר, oker davar, but in the area
of marriage they are able to מפקיע קידושין. mafki'a kiddushin. Now, why
are they able to in the area of marriage? So a classic
explanation is because anybody that marries, marries על דעת בית דין, al
da'as beis din, like we say nowadays כדת משה וישראל, kedas Moshe
v'Yisrael, and therefore if בית דין beis din in the end decides
they don't like it, they're able to uproot it. That's one explanation.
Okay, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara, says. אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי, amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said to
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, הא תינח דקדש בכספא, ha tina'is de'kadesh be'chaspa,
that works that they can uproot the marriage if he married with
money, because presumably the way רש"י Rashi explains this is because then
we know the principle of הפקר בית דין הפקר, hefker beis din
hefker, so they could retroactively say you never owned the ring. But
קדש בביאה מאי איכא למימר, kadesh be'vi'ah mai ika lemeimar, if he
married with an act of sex, how are they going to, what
mechanism are they going to use to uproot the קידושין? kiddushin? So
the גמרא Gemara says, שויוה רבנן לבעילתו בעילת זנות. shavyuha rabbanan leviaso
be'vias znus. Yes,
they will retroactively say that they will redefine the act and say
it was not an act of sex in the context of marriage,
it was a simple act of fornication, and therefore you were never
married. The Rabbis have the ability to redefine קידושין, kiddushin, but that's
not a sweeping ability of יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור דבר. yesh
koach beyad chachamim la'akor davar. Now I want to say one thing.
Obviously there's a big discussion of what the הפקעת קידושין hafkakas kiddushin
is, I gave you one explanation, but I should tell you two
things. First of all, again I want to repeat the רשב"א Rashba
said that the idea of הפקעת קידושין, hafkakas kiddushin, similar to what
תוספות Tosafos said about the idea of יש כח, is when you
have some fig leaf to hide behind. So here the fig leaf
is there was a גט. get. So even though דאורייתא the גט
get wasn't good, but we will be able to do הפקעת קידושין
hafkakas kiddushin behind the scenes and make it look like the גט
get was good.
Okay, as opposed to
just, right, exactly, as opposed to just a simple case of recalcitrant
husband, which is why some of the people that want to use
הפקעת קידושין hafkakas kiddushin want to say let's give a גט get
at the same time. Not husband give a גט, get, we'll give
a גט get for the husband, but it'll create that type of
a fig leaf. That's one point. But the second point I want
to say is תוספות Tosafos says that when the גמרא, Gemara you
know what the mechanism of הפקעת קידושין hafkakas kiddushin is? יש כח
ביד חכמים לעקור דבר מן התורה. yesh koach beyad chachamim la'akor davar
min hatorah. Any guesses what תוספות Tosafos says the reason is? What
does תוספות Tosafos say the reason is for that we believe the
עד אחד? ed echad? Remember what I told you at the beginning
of the שיעור? shiur? Why I believe the עד אחד? ed echad?
What? I gave you a whole list of reasons. But תוספות Tosafos
says the reason we believe the עד אחד ed echad is
יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור דבר מן התורה. yesh koach beyad chachamim
la'akor davar min hatorah. So תוספות Tosafos says the mechanism of הפקעת
קידושין hafkakas kiddushin is יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור דבר מן התורה.
be-yad hachamim la'akor davar min ha-Torah. So then how does the גמרא
Gemara answer back? Oh, but you know you see יש כח through
הפקעת קידושין hafkakas kiddushin because תוספות Tosafos says it's like the גמרא
Gemara said before about the case of מת מצוה. meis mitzvah. We're
allowed to do הפקעת קידושין hafkakas kiddushin when it's not obvious that
we're doing it. So therefore when we're allowed to do, I should
say, עקור דבר מן התורה oker davar min hatorah when it's not
obvious that we're doing it. So when we were saying you could
be מטמא metamei to this underage woman who's not really your wife,
it's because it's sort of like מת מצוה. meis mitzvah. When we're
saying this woman could remarry, it's not obvious we're עקור דבר oker
davar because we're הפקעת קידושין. hafkakas kiddushin. And somehow that's less עקור,
oker, that's less sort of a clear עקור דבר oker davar when
it's specifically about the institution of marriage than a blatant type of
עקור דבר. oker davar. So it's a little bit funny because both
of them seem to be pretty, I know it's not so obvious.
Meaning if people understand, oh, I get it, by marriage the Rabbis
have the right, it's not some sweeping obvious... yeah, I don't know.
Maybe again because of שויוה רבנן לבעילתו בעילת זנות, shavyuha rabbanan leviaso
be'vias znus,
because the Rabbis redefine what the act meant, they redefine who owned
the ring and therefore...
so can the Rabbis in some sort of rabbinic or בית דין
beis din figure out your marriage?
I guess something like that. Or because of what the גמרא Gemara
just said, because the Rabbis, it makes sense. they get to say
that you didn't own the ring, they get to say whether they
recognize it as ביאת מצווה bi'as mitzvah or ביאת זנות. bi'as zenus.
So anyway, תוספות Tosfos says that the mechanism of הפקעת קידושין hafka'as
kiddushin is in the end יש כוח, yesh koach, but again, this
is תוספות's Tosfos's point that יש כוח, yesh koach, not this תוספות,
Tosfos, there is a תוספות Tosfos that says it, not every תוספות
Tosfos says this, but there is תוספות, Tosfos, יש כוח yesh koach
works when it somehow seems to be some other mechanism going on.
And הפקעת קידושין hafka'as kiddushin because the rabbis redefine what was meant
by the ring and by the sex is that other mechanism. Okay,
so again we have two limits of יש כוח ביד חכמים: yesh
koach be-yad hachamim: one is בשב ואל תעשה and the other is
according to תוספות Tosfos when it looks like a legitimate mechanism. And
we also have this idea by the נביא Navi of a case
of מיגדר מילתא. migdar milsa. So if you, I know we're a
little over, but if you'll just give me two minutes we'll finish
this סוגיא. sugya The last case is תא שמע: tashma: אמר רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב שמעתי שבית דין מכין ועונשין שלא מן התורה. amar
Rabi Elazar ben Ya'akov shama'ati she-Beit Din makin ve-onshin she-lo min ha-Torah.
בית דין Beit Din give lashes and fine people and maybe even
execute people, not according to biblical law, ולא לעבור על דברי תורה,
velo la'avor al divrei Torah, not God forbid for the purpose of
violating Torah, אלא לעשות סייג לתורה, ela la'asot seyag la-Torah, but to
make a safeguard. Right? That's the word of like מיגדר מילתא, migdar
milsa, a protection, a fence. ומעשה באדם אחד שרכב על סוס בשבת
בימי יוונים. u-ma'aseh be-adam echad she-rachav al sus be-Shabbos b'yemei Yevanim.
There's a person who was riding on a horse on שבת, which
is only a rabbinic violation, in the time of the Greeks, in
the Hellenists, when there was all that assimilation going on. והביאוהו לבית
דין וסקלוהו, ve-hevi'uhu le-Beit Din ve-sikluho, and they brought him to בית
דין Beit Din and they executed him, they stoned him. לא מפני
שראוי לכך, lo mipnei she-ra'uy lekach, not because he legally was deserving
of that, אלא שהשעה צריכה לכך, ela she-hasha'ah tzericha lekach, but because
it was an exigent circumstance. ושוב מעשה באדם אחד שהטיח באשתו תחת
התאנה. ve-shuv ma'aseh be-adam echad she-hetiach be-ishto tachas ha-te'enah.
A man had sex with his wife, it was with his wife,
but it was out there in the field under the, what do
you call it? The fig tree. והביאוהו לבית דין והלקוהו, ve-hevi'uhu le-Beit
Din ve-hilkuho, and they brought him to בית דין Beit Din and
they gave him lashes. לא מפני שראוי לכך, lo mipnei she-ra'uy lekach,
not because legally that was deserving, אלא שהשעה צריכה לכך, ela she-hasha'ah
tzericha lekach, but because it was an exigent circumstance. People were being
too, you know, free with, sexually unrestrained. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ah, you see they can do what they want? No, מיגדר מילתא
שאני. migdar milsa shani. That is not changing the legal system, that
is actually an exigent circumstance and it's a particular punishment as opposed
to actually changing the law in a systematic way. So the גמרא
concludes with not being able to prove יש כוח ביד חכמים לעקור
דבר מן התורה, yesh koach be-yad hachamim la'akor davar min ha-Torah, being
a lot of evidence but not having a black and white answer.
We have conceded that it does work in a case of שב
ואל תעשה, it works in cases of מיגדר מילתא, migdar milsa, exigent
circumstances, and according to תוספות Tosfos it works when there is some
type of a mechanism that makes it look not as a clear
violation. And there's a debate in the ראשונים Rishonim whether at the
end of the day do we פסקן pasken in general יש כוח
yesh koach or not. The גמרא ends inconclusively. It doesn't end no.
It concedes many cases in terms of the broad sense. It's inconclusive
whether יש כוח yesh koach or not כוח koach ביד חכמים לעקור
דבר מן התורה. This is a very major ש"ס Shas סוגיא about
this really important idea about rabbinic power and we will end with
that for today.